

#### PhD, Assistant Professor, Researcher

Department of Computer Science, Sapienza University of Rome, Via Salaria 113, 00198 Rome, Italy Department of Legal and Economic Sciences, UnitelmaSapienza, Piazza Sassari 4, 00161 Rome, Italy

💌 cascio@di.uniroma1.it - marco.cascio@unitelmasapienza.it | 🎁 http://visionlab.di.uniroma1.it/ - https://www.unitelmasapienza.it/marco-cascio/

## **Summary**

In December 2022, I became an Assistant Professor at the University of Rome UnitelmaSapienza. Additionally, I continue to support the Department of Computer Science at Sapienza University of Rome, where I have been a member of the Computer Vision Laboratory (VisionLab) since 2018. My research primarily focuses on Computer Vision, Artificial Intelligence, Machine/Deep Learning, and Signal Processing.

#### Languages:

• Italian: Mother tongue

· English: Proficient

## **Education**

#### **Department of Computer Science**

Sapienza University of Rome

PhD in Computer Science (with honors)

2018-2021

- Thesis Title: Person Re-ID through Radio Biometric Signatures, Human Silhouette and Skeleton Video Synthesis through Wi-Fi Signals
- · Advisors: Luigi Cinque, Chiara Petrioli
- Co-advisor: Danilo Avola

#### **Department of Computer Science**

Sapienza University of Rome

2015-2018

MASTER DEGREE COMPUTER SCIENCE (CUM LAUDE)

- Thesis Title: Un Approccio Innovativo basato su Deep Learning per la Classificazione di Human Action
- Advisor: Luigi CinqueCo-advisor: Danilo Avola

#### **Department of Computer Science**

BACHELOR DEGREE COMPUTER SCIENCE

University of Messina

2009-2015

- Thesis Title: Algoritmi di Risoluzione di Anagrammi
- · Advisor: Giacomo Fiumara

## **Experience**

### **Department of Law and Economics - Department of Computer Science**

UnitelmaSapienza - Sapienza
University of Rome

 ${\tt Assistant\ Professor,\ Academic\ Discipline\ INF/01\ INFORMATICS}$ 

RESEARCHER, ACADEMIC DISCIPLINES INF/01 INFORMATICS - ING-INF/05

2022 - present

#### **Department of Computer Science**

 $Research \ Fellow, Academic \ Disciplines \ INF/01 \ INFORMATICS-ING-INF/05, Project \ Title: \ Human \ Silhouette \ Video \ Academic \ Disciplines \ INF/01 \ INFORMATICS-ING-INF/05, Project \ Title: \ Human \ Silhouette \ Video \ Academic \ Disciplines \ INF/01 \ INFORMATICS-ING-INF/05, Project \ Title: \ Human \ Silhouette \ Video \ Academic \ Disciplines \ Video \ Academic \ Video \$ 

SYNTHESIS FROM WI-FI SIGNALS

Sapienza University of Rome

2022

2021

## **Department of Computer Science**

RESEARCH FELLOW, ACADEMIC DISCIPLINES INF/01 INFORMATICS - ING-INF/05, PROJECT TITLE: DEVICE-FREE WI-FI HUMAN

DETECTION, LOCALIZATION, POSE ESTIMATION AND PERSON RE-IDENTIFICATION BASED ON CSI AND DEEP LEARNING

STRATEGIES

Sapienza University of Rome

JULY 3, 2023 MARCO CASCIO · CURRICULUM VITAE 1

#### **Department of Computer Science**

Sapienza University of Rome

RESEARCH FELLOW, ACADEMIC DISCIPLINES INF/01 INFORMATICS - ING-INF/05, PROJECT TITLE: DEVICE-FREE WI-FI HUMAN

DETECTION, LOCALIZATION, POSE ESTIMATION AND PERSON RE-IDENTIFICATION BASED ON CSI AND DEEP LEARNING

STRATEGIES

2020

#### **Department of Computer Science**

Sapienza University of Rome

SCHOLARSHIP, APPLICATION OF MACHINE LEARNING TECHNIQUES FOR UNDERWATER SYSTEMS OPTIMIZATION

2019

#### **Department of Computer Science**

Sapienza University of Rome

SCHOLARSHIP, DEVELOPMENT OF MACHINE LEARNING TECHNIQUES FOR UNDERWATER MOBILE NETWORKS OPTIMIZATION

## **Research Projects**

### **DRAGONS - DRone Aerial imaGes seGmentatiON System**

Ministry of Defense

WORK PACKAGE LEADER - SENIOR R&D ENGINEER

2023 - present

- Design and description of the project use cases
- · Design and development of novel deep learning algorithms for low altitude images segmentation

#### **SEARCHER - Smart unmannEd AeRial vehiCles for Human like monitoRing**

Ministry of Defense

WORK PACKAGE LEADER - SENIOR R&D ENGINEER 2022 - present

- Coordination of the WP2 group
- · Study and analysis of the state-of-the art on the anomaly detection, novelty detection, and attention mechanism algorithms
- Design and development of novel deep learning algorithms

### PON SMARTOUR - Piattaforma per la promozione del turismo culturale attraverso l'impiego di tecnologie innovative

MIUR

2020

SENIOR R&D ENGINEER

- Study and analysis of the state of the art on wireless sensing and monitoring technologies
- Design and implementation of a Wi-Fi Person Re-Identification algorithm
- Lab testing of the proposed solution

### MEDUSA - Monitoring maritimE areas by a cooperative Distributed Unmanned System made of heterogeneous Assets

Stato Maggiore della Marina (MARISTAT)

SENIOR R&D ENGINEER 2018-2020

- Study and analysis of the state of the art on the underwater anomaly detection algorithms
- · Design and implementation of novel computer vision algorithms for underwater anomaly detection
- · Lab testing of the proposed solutions

#### TEAM - Tecnologie Emergenti per l'Archeologia Marina

SENIOR R&D ENGINEER

2014-2020

- Study and analysis of the state of the art on the underwater novelty/anomaly detection and localization algorithms
- Design and implementation of novel computer vision algorithms for underwater novelty/anomaly detection and localization
- · Lab testing of the proposed solutions

#### **RA2M - Augmented Reality for Mobile Applications**

Ministry of Defense

SENIOR R&D ENGINEER 2016-2018

- Study and analysis of the state of the art on visual detection and classification algorithms
- · Design and development of algorithms for detection and classification of unexploded devices
- · Lab testing of the proposed solutions

## Teaching Experience \_\_\_\_\_

#### Teacher at the Master in Data and Process Analysis and Modeling: Methods and Models

MODULO 7 - ANALISI DEI DATI TESTUALI, MODULO 8 - ANALISI DI RETI SOCIALI

UnitelmaSapienza, University of Rome

2023 - present

#### Lecturer on Informatica e Tecnologie della Comunicazione Digitale

BACHELOR DEGREE IN COMMUNICATION, TECHNOLOGIES AND DIGITAL CULTURES

Department of Communication and Social Research (CoRiS), Sapienza University of Rome

2023

### **Lecturer on Digital Content Processing (Course Language: English)**

MASTER DEGREE IN ECONOMY AND COMMUNICATION FOR MANAGEMENT AND INNOVATION

Department of Management, Sapienza University of Rome

2018-2021

#### Lecturer on Informatica e Tecnologie della Comunicazione Digitale

BACHELOR DEGREE IN PUBLIC AND CORPORATE COMMUNICATION

Department of Communication and Social Research (CoRiS), Sapienza University of Rome

2020

### Lecturer on Informatica e Tecnologie della Comunicazione Digitale

BACHELOR DEGREE IN COMMUNICATION, TECHNOLOGIES AND DIGITAL CULTURES

Department of Communication and Social Research (CoRiS), Sapienza University of Rome

2020

#### Teacher at ITHUM/ICTAcademy (Course Language: English)

MASTER & EXECUTIVE PROGRAMME IN CYBER SCIENCE, MODULE A - INTERNET BASED SYSTEMS & PROGRAMMING, COURSE:

ITHUM SRL, Rome

2018

# Speaker Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Ital-IA Conference

ORAL PRESENTATION OF PAPER "MACHINE LEARNING FOR REAL TIME ANALYSIS OF SOCIAL DATA FOR DISASTER MANAGEMENT"

2019

## Other Experience \_\_\_\_\_

PhD Summer School University of Udine

INTERNATIONAL SUMMER SCHOOL ON ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE (AI-DLDA 2020)

2020

## **Society Memberships, Honors & Awards**

2020 -	Member, IEEE Organization		
present			
2022	Award for innovation and technological impact, PNRM Project Title: "INFERENCE - wI-fi sensing For		
	pErson Re-idENtifiCation and human image synthEsis", Ministry of Defense		
2022	<b>Paper selected for Newsletter,</b> in <i>IEEE Biometrics Council Newsletter</i> , Paper Title: "Person Re-Identification		
	through Wi-Fi Extracted Radio Biometric Signatures"		
2020	Scholarship for International Summer School on Artificial Intelligence, University of Udine		
2019	Award for innovation and technological impact, PNRM Project Title: "VERIFY - deVice frEe peRson		
	re-Identification sYstem", Ministry of Defense		
2019	<b>Research grant "Avvio alla Ricerca",</b> Project Title: "Device-Free Wi-Fi Human Detection, Localization, Pose		
	Estimation and Re-Identification based on CSI and Deep Learning strategies", Sapienza University of Rome		

## Program Committees and Editorial Boards \_\_\_\_\_

2023	<b>Program Committee</b> , in International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing, 1st International	Udine, Italy
2023	Workshop on Advances in Image Satellite Processing and Interpretation	ourre, italy
2023	<b>Guest Editor</b> , in <i>Journal of Computational and Cognitive Engineering</i> , Special Issue "Current Trends and	JCCF
	New Frontiers of Brain-Computer Interface"	JCCL
2022	<b>Guest Editor,</b> in <i>Remote Sensing Journal</i> (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 168, Impact Factor: 5.349), Special Issue	Remote Sensing
	"Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAV): New Solutions and Applications for Real-Life Tasks"	
2022	<b>Program Committee</b> , in International Conference on Military Communications and Information Systems	Udine, Italy

## **Academic Professional Service**

Serving as reviewer for the following journals and conferences:

- IEEE Reviewer
  - Transactions on Multimedia
  - Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems
- Springer Nature Reviewer
  - Artificial Intelligence Review
- MDPI Reviewer
  - Electronics
  - Information
  - Sensors

## Skills \_\_\_\_\_

Programming: C/C++, Python, C#, Java, Matlab, Swift, HTML, SQL

**Frameworks:** OpenCV, Pytorch, Keras, Tensorflow, Caffe, Scikit-Learn, Numpy **IDE & Tools:** Visual Studio, NetBeans, Eclipse, IntelliJ, Pycharm, Android Studio, Xcode

**Operating Systems:** Windows, Linux Ubuntu, macOS

### **Personal Statement**

I am an Assistant Professor at the University of Rome UnitelmaSapienza, and I also support the Department of Computer Science at Sapienza University of Rome where I have been a member of the Computer Vision Laboratory (VisionLab) since 2018. My research interests lie in the fields of Computer Vision, Artificial Intelligence, and Signal Processing. Over the past few years, I have worked on several research projects focused on wireless sensing and image/video content understanding applications. In the area of wireless sensing, my in-depth research on Wi-Fi signals has opened up new possibilities for surveillance applications. I have developed a novel signal-based sensing modality for tasks such as Person Re-Identification and Video Synthesis, which traditionally rely on visual information. This approach increases radio signals with visual appearance, expanding the range of available information. In the field of image/video content understanding, I have developed Event Recognition methods using Machine/Deep Learning strategies and visual data. These methods have been applied to applications such as UAV monitoring and human behavior understanding. My current research interests include machine/deep learning, scene and event understanding, pattern analysis, signal processing, anomaly detection and localization, human-computer interaction, biometric analysis, medical image analysis, multimodal fusion models, robotics, object tracking, and surveillance systems.

### **Publications**

#### **Journals**

- [1] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, and Chiara Petrioli. "Person Re-Identification Through Wi-Fi Extracted Radio Biometric Signatures". In: *IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security*, vol. 17, pp. 1145–1158, 2022 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 154, Impact Factor: 7.231)
- [2] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, Gian Luca Foresti, Marco Raoul Marini, Fabrizio Rossi. "Real-Time Deep Learning Method for Automated Detection and Localization of Structural Defects in Manufactured Products". In: *Computers & Industrial Engineering*, vol. 172, pp. 108512, 2022 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 148, Impact Factor: 7.180, Peer review: Double-blind)
- [3] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, and Gian Luca Foresti. "Affective Action and Interaction Recognition by Multi-view Representation Learning from Handcrafted Low-level Skeleton Features". In: *International Journal of Neural Systems*, pp. 1–23, 2022 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 67, Impact Factor: 6.325)
- [4] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, and Gian Luca Foresti. "Human Silhouette and Skeleton Video Synthesis Through Wi-Fi Signals". In: *International Journal of Neural Systems*, vol. 32, no. 05, p. 2250015, 2022 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 67, Impact Factor: 6.325)
- [5] Danilo Avola, Irene Cannistraci, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Anxhelo Diko, Alessio Fagioli, Gian Luca Foresti, Romeo Lanzino, Maurizio Mancini, Alessio Mecca, Daniele Pannone. "A Novel GAN-Based Anomaly Detection and Localization Method for Aerial Video Surveillance at Low Altitude". In: *Remote Sensing*, vol. 14, no. 16, pp. 1-18, 2022 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 168, Impact Factor: 5.349)
- [6] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, and Gian Luca Foresti. "LieToMe: An Ensemble Approach for Deception Detection from Facial Cues". In: *International Journal of Neural Systems*, vol. 31, no.02, p. 2050068, 2021 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 70, Impact Factor: 6.325)
- [7] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Gian Luca Foresti, and Daniele Pannone. "Machine Learning for Video Event Recognition". In: *Integrated Computer-Aided Engineering*, vol. 28, no. 03, pp. 309–332, 2021 (Quartile: Q2, h-index: 47, Impact Factor: 6.137)
- [8] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Gian Luca Foresti, Cristiano Massaroni, and Emanuele Rodolà. "2-D Skeleton-Based Action Recognition via Two-Branch Stacked LSTM-RNNs". In: *IEEE Transactions on Multimedia*, vol. 22, no. 10, pp. 2481–2496, 2020 (Quartile: Q1, h-index: 144, Impact Factor: 6.513)

#### **Conferences**

- [9] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, Gian Luca Foresti, Marco Raoul Marini, and Daniele Pannone. "Analyzing EEG Data with Machine and Deep Learning: A Benchmark". In: *Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP)*, Springer International Publishing, pp. 335–345, 2022 (Peer review: Double-blind)
- [10] Danilo Avola, Marco Bernardi, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Gian Luca Foresti, and Cristiano Massaroni. "A New Descriptor for Keypoint-Based Background Modeling". In: *Image Analysis and Processing* (*ICIAP*), Springer International Publishing, pp. 15–25, 2019 (Peer review: Double-blind)
- [11] Danilo Avola, **Marco Cascio**, Luigi Cinque, Alessio Fagioli, Gian Luca Foresti, and Cristiano Massaroni. "Master and Rookie Networks for Person Re-identification". In: *Computer Analysis of Images and Patterns (CAIP)*, Springer International Publishing, pp. 470–479, 2019
- [12] M. Vernier, **Marco Cascio**, Gian Luca Foresti, and M. Farinosi. "Machine Learning for Real-Time Analysis of Social Data for Disaster Management". In: *Ital-IA 2019*, pp. 1–2, 2019 (White paper)